[music]
Welcome. Thanks for coming. Um,
basically what we're talking about is
uh, uh, we've taken Agentic AI beyond
just coding. We use it for architecture
work. We use it for planning large
projects. We use it for market analysis
for um moving apps to different tool
sets or different products. Um and we
use it on legacy code. We don't um there
seems to be this uh prevailing uh uh
thought out there that AI agentic AI
just doesn't work with legacy code.
That's not my experience. All right. I
take that back. It is my experience on
some
tooling combinations that I've tried it
on that I've had less than stellar
success with. Um, but my current tech
stack I've I've had uh very good success
with legacy code. So, I'm going for a
little bit of interaction today. Show of
hands. Who has used or at least
experimented with Claude Flow before?
Okay, one. Great. Applause.
Um, who has used Claude code?
Good. You've got a leg up because what
actually happens is Claude Flow runs an
army of Claude Code agents under the
covers. All right. Um, it manages that
for you. Um, but if you didn't raise
your hand, don't worry. Um,
there is uh um I I will boost you and
get you up to speed. Um, enough about
me. I'm a professional geek. If you look
me up on LinkedIn or something, it kind
of makes you to believe that I'm more of
a manager type. And I only do white
shirt stuff grudgingly. I'd rather code.
But, you know, enough about me.
What we're going to do today is I need
to
before we get into
um applying claude flow and claude code
to a legacy codebase, I need to level
set at modernization means different
things to different people. All right,
so I need to clarify my terms a little
bit there. And for the people that
didn't raise their hands, I need to give
you a little bit more about what Claude
code is and what Claude code does for me
and why I use it in this mix. And then
we're going to and we're not going to
that's not that's just level setting. Um
we're going to spend the bulk of our
time uh basically um showing you what it
can do with a legacy code base, a
substantial one. All right. Um, the
Orienteer uh CRM basically is a CRM that
as far as I can tell was largely
abandoned in about 2020. It's a very
large Java application. And I chose Java
not because I have any religious
affiliation for it, but I chose Java
because a lot of Java is out there and
that's a large percentage of our legacy
code base. All right. And so that's
that's kind of why um
I chose it.
I see a lot of people um taking photos.
That QR code
gets you to a web page that has a copy
of this deck.
It has
um active links. And you might notice
that um I'm pretty good about uh putting
active links in my um decks.
So um if you take a picture, what you
really want to do is take a picture of
that and it gives you uh it gets you to
all this. And if there is some type of
trouble I need to start my timer. If
there's some type of trouble and you
can't get to the deck, contact me on
LinkedIn or whatnot. I'll make sure that
you get it. Um,
but basically app monetization to me is
a lot of people when they when they
think about that term, they think, well,
I'm just updating my tech stack. I that
might be true, but that's more of a
symptom or a byproduct of app
monitoriization rather than the uh
rather than the goal. Um, usually what
customers mean when they approach us
about, well, we want to modernize this
app, what they really mean is we want it
to move to the cloud or cube and we want
it to be able to take advantage of
dynamic scaling and higher availability
features that those platforms have. All
right. And lots of legacy code bases
cannot do that. Um so in in rather than
concentrating on the tech stack for an
app moni monitorization
um effort and I need to learn how to say
that um it's more application
portability than anything else. The
other thing that happens with legacy
code bases is they become hard to change
and everybody cringes when new releases
come out because you don't know what's
going to break. And in other words, what
what really comes along with this
application monitorization effort um is
a code management uh um change as well.
Um another show of hands.
Who is familiar with the concept of a 12
factor app or the 12 factor application
principles? Okay, a few people um back
in 2012 um Heroku which got bought out
by Salesforce um a bunch of people there
put together a specific um list of 12
characteristics that applications should
have if they are going to be hosted in
the cloud and be able to take good
advantage of resiliency features or
dynamic scaling features. and in in
essence be portable. Um, make your
hosting environment a choice rather than
a requirement that's baked in. And
that's well documented and there's a
link there for it.
Um, and we talked a little bit about
this. Um, anyway, um, companies don't
modernize just for fun. They modernize
because they're in a pickle. All right.
apps are too hard to change and they
want to get to this cloud thing and
they've recognized that lifting and
shifting doesn't really work as well as
people think they would work. Um, all
right. [snorts]
Why do I use Claude Flow? What is Claude
Flow? What it does is it runs a team of
Cloud Code agents under the under the
covers. out of the box. It just works
with, you know, you basically install
it. There's a minor configuration thing
with cloud code that you got to do, but
you are just off and running in minutes,
not hours or days.
And I use it to get stuff done, right? I
don't want to spend time on plumbing.
Um, there. And it's not that I'm just
turning my nose up at it. It's just I my
focus is different. Okay. Um and by
default, right out of the box, um
basically Claude Flow will manage the
team so I don't have to. Um, for you
cursor users out there, um, Cursor just
within the past few weeks released a
feature where you can within the IDE run
multiple agents to do different things
on your codebase at the same time.
That's a great improvement and I'm not
dinging it. But what that scene forces
me to do is it forces me to micromanage
the team. That's a function that
Cloudflow does for me.
All right. Um, of the agents that get
assigned to your task, what happens is
there is a coordinator agent. He looks
at what I ask the team to do and he
decides, well, you know, I need a tester
agent, I need a coder agent, I need a
project manager agent, I need an analyst
agent, I need a researcher agent or
whatever it is depending upon what I
asked. I didn't have to micromanage
those decisions. with clawed flow I can
but to date I have not had a reason to
do it. Um and it's the ease of use thing
that draws me. I find myself I'm not
spending time in the plumbing. I'm
spending time on what I really want to
be doing on the outcomes that I want.
Okay.
Now let's turn the corner.
um application modernization I've
defined um cloud flow I've told you what
it is let's do some real work with it
all right and this is analytical work or
something um when before this tooling
came along when we got app monitor
monitorization projects uh for clients
the very first thing that we would do is
figure out okay what kind of team do I
need to put together to go audit that
course that code base to know what kind
of nasties we got to fix in order to
modernize it. In other words, the way to
state that is where does it violate the
12 factor principles.
Okay, so what I did is I basically
crafted a series of English statements
and there's a link for the detailed
instructions. I've cleaned them up a
little bit so I could present them on a
slide, but I basically just asked my
team, "Hey, give me a 12 factor
analysis. By the way, the 12 factor
principles are nicely defined on the
web, so you can go read them and look
them up. And by the way, I don't want
you to change the application. I don't
want you to mess with that in any way. I
just want to know where the application
violates 12 factor principles. So I know
what I got to go fix to have this
application do dynamic scaling and high
availability and all the other things
that we would like when we get it to the
cloud.
And I basically gave that to my team and
about 10 minutes later,
literally 10 11 minutes later, I get a
series of markdown documents and it's
way too much for me to present on a
slide like this. What I've given you is
just the um summary in the uh at the
very top of the uh um executive summary,
but it basically went through all 12
factors. It looked in detail at all of
them and it basically told me where the
codebase violates the 12 factor
principles. And further on down, it'll
give me exact details on exactly where
the application
broke down where it violated the
principles and what it thinks it would
have to change. And when I get something
like this, I just don't take it. I I
mean, even when I had human teams doing
this, right, um, and I would get their
analysis, I wouldn't trust it. I'd trust
but verify. All right? So I basically,
and we can't do that today, there's no
time. But I basically went through the
20 or 30 pages that got generated out of
this and I went through line by line and
it largely hung together. Now, a couple
of the uh a couple of the uh uh you
notice how it kind of graded things into
categories, statuses. Um, in a couple of
instances it flagged things that are
critical that I might have I might have
uh um basically uh upgraded to poor or
something along those lines. But beyond
those knits and I would have that
criticism of what a human team gave me
anyway, right? um it largely hung
together and basically what um what it
uh
basically uh told me is that uh the app
doesn't support dynamic scaling. It uses
stateful sessions. There are ways to fix
that. It has hard-coded credentials. It
doesn't have health checks. Um basically
there's no way to it's monolithic.
there's no way to individually scale
pieces.
And so what I did next
and that, you know, it took me about an
hour to go through it, but it took my
team only 10 minutes to come come come
deliver it.
What I did next is I said, "Okay, let's
assume I'm going to fix each and every
problem that you found." All right. So
use the analysis that you neatly
documented in this folder and give me an
execution plan. Don't change anything
yet, but I want to know what do you
suggest in terms of order that I go
tackle these changes and how do I do it
safely? And oh by the way, add an
acceptance automated acceptance test
suite because when I go actually go
change this for real, I don't want to
break anything or at least I want a
chance of catching things I break before
I before I deploy it because you know a
lot of times uh legacy code bases don't
really have good automated test suites.
All right. So I tack that on to any
monitor monitoriization effort that I
do. And so I nicely
verbalized these instructions. I cleaned
them up for the slide, but you can look
at exactly
what I gave it
and it basically came out um with uh
estimated human labor. broke out what
what was human, what was uh what was um
um agentbased and where where what my
runtime costs would be and what it
thought based on prevailing market rates
it would cost me. Now
that's claude code in its training
talking. That's nothing I would just
point blank take to uh take to uh uh
management to go budget.
But on the other hand um basically and
in fact the first time I planned
I had it plan um the implementation I
screwed up. I forgot to tell it that oh
by the way don't assume that human
coders are doing all of this. assume
that I am using agentic engineers using
agentic
um practices and using cloud flow and
claude code.
All right. Um and so I had to I had to
do a couple uh um revisions of that. Um
and incidentally um you've all been
there, right? As an architect, I go take
a plan or take the uh effects of a
proposed change up to management. They
have they first of all, they don't like
the price.
Secondly, um
they their minds start shifting about
okay, what if we didn't do this part of
what it's recommending or we didn't do
that part of what it's recommending? In
the old days when I'm running a human
team to go do this, people scurry off
and they go do that. In a few days I'll
have my answer right
with my Cloudflow team.
Basically, a few minutes later, 10, 20
minutes later, I've got answers to them.
Now, I have to go through those answers
to make sure that it didn't hallucinate
or make sure it I I I verbalize the
changes I wanted it to to to game out
for me. But, um, basically that opens up
the world. I don't like going through
and writing 80page finding documents.
That's not something I consider fun. I
I'm just going to guess that you don't
consider that fun either. Um but this
this whole world basically makes more
possible.
Now let's uh we talked a little bit
about this um reframing the question if
I were going to give this to a human
team could I trust it more? And the
reality is I'm going to still trust but
verify. Um, basically all forecasts,
whether they're human-driven or whether
they're my Claude team drives it, have
forecasts with error rates. There's
there's nobody has a crystal ball and my
Cloudflow team doesn't have a crystal
ball either. All right. Um, what I do
like there are a couple of advantages.
Claude has no concept of corporate
politics.
If I have a human team, they will know
what the higherups think or the
higherups will go down below me and say,
you know, skew the the the decision down
to to to these facts instead of uh
instead of what what you know to be
true. Claude ignores all that. No
corporate politics, no corporate bias.
All right. Um, and it's unspeetable
speed, which means that a those managers
can ask more questions because I have
the ability to game out more scenarios
more quickly.
And on their side, role play for an
upper level management person, right?
They are hesitant to ask those scenarios
be gamed out because they know they're
paying for it. they know in a all human
situation I've got to go back to the
team and people scramble for for hours
or days and go figure that out at a
consulting rate that they don't really
like to pay. But on the other hand, if
they know that I'm going to take that
back to my team, which is a clawed flow
team, I can have that back well within a
day and it doesn't cost them nearly as
much. So they can ask more questions. It
doesn't matter.
Okay.
When you talk about app monitorization,
bringing that up a level invariably,
especially when they when they consider
the pain of modernizing the app,
somebody comes up with the idea of what
if we just move these people to a
different product. We we configure a SAS
product that kind of close to uh close
to fits what uh what our business people
are doing and we move them to that
instead. All right. So, okay,
my team can handle that too. All right.
So, what I basically did is I verbalized
um those instructions. I told my team to
go out into the world um with this
codebase, go find available SAS products
that I could potentially move users to
prioritize
um cons conserving um features.
Um in other words, we don't we we got to
meet the business need, right? Users got
to do what they have to do anyway. I
can't I can't get out of that. um and
basically
um basically uh um prioritize
um safety and and and and moving uh that
kind of thing. And I'm running short of
time, so I'm going to speed up just a
Okay. Um to finish this thought out,
basically it went away for it took it a
little bit longer this time. And it went
away for about 15 20 minutes and it came
back with okay these are the top uh
three um SAS alternatives I see given
the features of orienteer. Now it was
operating my team was operating with
their hands tied behind their back
because had this been a real
installation.
I could have basically
uh I I I I could have given it
information about okay my users use
these features but they don't use these
features right and that might have
influenced the analysis. I didn't have
that. So basically it came up with uh a
recommendation and went through in
detail on all of them and it's
recommending Salesforce based on what I
gave it.
Key takeaways.
All right.
This world goes beyond coding.
For architects, you can use ar you could
do architectural planning and oftentimes
my team comes up with ideas that I might
not have thought of and are worth
listening to. Okay. Uh for team leads,
um you're dealing with management and
it's nice to know how big this effort
is. You know, is it small? Is it medium?
Is it large? What size effort are you
looking at? and you got to be able to
socialize that up to your executive
management team. Um, for agile teams, it
basically helps you break out stories.
In this world, stories tend to be a
little bit larger than they would in a
whole um in a whole entirely human team
world, right? I look at it as a
continuum. In a human team world, we
size stories so that they take less than
two days or something along those lines.
versus the the oneshot deals that you
see publicized. Um, to me, what what
ends up happening is this world moves us
along the continuum where my team can
handle slightly larger stories than they
used to be able to handle, but we're
still not getting to the oneshot deal.
All right. Um and I am probably because
I started my um
talk late um or timer late. Thanks for
coming. I'm around. Feel free to contact
me with questions or anything if you
have them. I would uh very happily uh
help you out and get you any information
that you need. Thanks for coming.
[applause]
So thank you Derek. Uh we have time for
one question. The other presenters are
setting up so I'll come to you. Um so
Baroo and others sorry just go ahead.
You're happy to set up while
>> Thank you. I thought that was great. Um
what about if you're looking at adopting
a framework like say spec kit and you
want to use specit and claude code would
claude flow compete with that have
contention with that or could it be
integrated
>> into a spec framework
>> um
>> I missed part of your question I'm sorry
>> so I mean so imagine you are adopting a
framework like spec kit okay
>> specbased framework for a development
because you moved on from vibe.
Would they coexist
or would they overlap?
>> I think you could make it co coexist. I
think what I'd have to do and I'm I
haven't tried that specifically. So I'm
leaving the realm of what my experience
is and telling you what I would try. I
would tell my team about the cloud uh
about the uh spec framework and about
any spec framework artifacts that might
already exist. I would tell it how it
should interpret those and how it should
use those. Um and I would see what it
comes up with and I would let it work on
its own feature branch. So if I didn't
like what it came up with, I would try
again. And on some pivot like that, I
would expect that Derek would have to
try a couple of times before I got
something that that worked.
That would be my that that's what I
would try.
>> Fair enough. Thank you.
[music]